# 大家好 現在快冬天啦 冬笋都已經出來啦
Hi everyone! The winter is coming and the bamboo shoots are already coming out.
# 在這個竹林裡面
They’re in this bamboo forest.
# 我們去挖一點 回來 煮中午飯
Let’s go and dig some, for our lunch.
# 要不然菜都沒得吃哦
Otherwise we have nothing for our lunch.
# 這裡有野獸
There are beasts,
# 野獸出沒
beasts in this area.
# 應該有竹笋哦
There should be some bamboo shoots.
# 誒
Ay?
# 你看 這就有一個
Look! Right here is one.
# 小小的 竹笋
A very small one, small bamboo shoot
# 那麼小
It’s so small.
# 自己冒出來的
You out youself.
# 這個你能怪我哦
So don't blame me.
# 那麼小
It’s so small.
# 那麼小也不放過
But size doesn’t matter.
# 現在還沒下雨
There hasn’t been any rain.
# 肯定是沒下雨 所以一個都沒有
I’m sure that there has been no rain. That’s way I can’t find even one.
# 找不到
Nothing
# 下次再來
Let’s come again later.
# 這樣怎麼搞呢
What should I do then?
# 剛剛來的時候就挖了一個
I've dug one when we came in.
# 就這一個啦
But that’s all.
# 一個都沒挖到 這個還絆了一下我的腳
Not even one. And this one has even tripped on me.
# 過幾天我再來
Let me come again a few days later.
# 現在還沒長出來
They haven’t even come out.
# 太猴急了我
I am too impatient.
# 下次來
Next time
# 你看 這個狗 坐在這裡一動不動
Look! This dog, he’s sitting here, like a statue.
# 呵呵
Hmhm
# 不吭不聲 也不叫也不閙
He’s not barking, not shouting, not yelping, not yelling,
# 坐在這裡像個孩子一樣
just sitting here, like a kid.
# 唉 走啦 回家啦
Ay! Let’s go, let’s go home.
# 一個都沒得到 下次來
Not even one. Let’s come again next time.
# 拿來西
Pack the things.
# 開花了哦
It has blossomed.
# 有沒捉到
Caught it?
# 那麼小
It’s so small.
# 它這種不重的
This kind of duck won’t be too heavy.
# 才好吃的 有沒三斤
The smaller ones taste better. Is it even a kilogram and a half?
# 最多
At most one and a half
At most
# 這樣的才漂亮
This size is the prettiest.
# 剛好叫我們村的老劉 抓了他隻鴨子
I just asked Liu in my village, for a duck from him.
# 跟他一說 他馬上抓給我啦
He caught me one immediately once I asked him.
# 今天就吃你 不然沒菜吃啊
You’ll be our lunch today. Otherwise we have nothing to eat.
# 你看
Look!
# 搞定啦
Done!
# 很小的 這個子鴨來的
It’s really small. It’s a baby duck.
# 我那天還買了兩個小鵝在這裡
I bought two little geese a few days ago.
# 那麼小
They’re so small.
# 這種鵝養大了很好吃的哦 它是小獅鵝
This kind of geese will be very tasty when they grow up. They are “lion geese”.
# 我們這邊叫獅鵝 土鵝來的
Here we call them “lion geese”. They’re native here.
# 你同類的手
Your buddy’s hand
# 給個盤子 那個 幫我拿來盤子來
Give me a pot. That one. Fetch me that pot.
# 煮 煮 煮掉這個鵝
Cook, cook, cook this geese.
# 煮掉這個鵝 是不是 嗯 它還小
You mean cook the geese, don’t you?
Um!
They’re still small.
# 你想吃鵝肉了是不是 嗯
You want geese, don’t you?
Um!
# 這個鴨子也可以吃噠 要不要這個鴨子吃
This duck is also nice. You want duck?
# 我想吃豬豬
I wanna eat the piggies.
# 甚麼 你想吃豬是不是 嗯
What? You wanna eat the pigs, don’t you?
Um!
# 豬在上面 那麼大的豬你怎麼吃的完
The pigs are up there. They’re so big, You can’t finish them.
# 我們今天吃鴨子好不好
Let’s have duck today, shall we?
# 你要吃豬 這個不是
Your want pork. But this is not.
# 這個不是 這是鴨子
This is not. This is duck.
# 搞一點這個子薑
Put some, some young ginger.
# 這種子薑才靚
This kind of young ginger is really beautiful.
# 這個子薑都有點老了
This young ginger is a bit old.
# 爸爸 幹嘛
Daddy!
What’s up?
# 把它放到這裡先
Put it here first.
# 加點油
Put some oil.
# 把生薑炒香先
Let me fry the ginger first.
# 把這個鴨子直接放下去
Then put in the duck right away.
# 加點鹽
Put some salt.
# 就這樣 差不多
Alright. Should be enough.
# 放點酒
Put some cooking wine.
# 放點醬油
Put some soy sauce.
# 顏色都出來啦
The colour is now coming out.
# 給你們喝啦 喝醉了才更好吃
I let you drink some beer. You would be even more tasty after getting drunk.
# 熟啦熟啦
It’s done, it’s done.
# 子薑燜鴨
Stewed duck with young ginger.
# 搞塊 搞塊肉吃一下
Let me have, have a piece of meat.
# 可以哦 真的
Not bad, really.
# 有啤酒的味道
There's flavour of beer.
# 爛啦
It’s soft now.
# 嗯 我牙不好
Um! My teeth are not good.
# 它這個要牙好一點才吃的到
It needs better teeth to chew it.
# 燜那麼久還不爛
Why didn't it become soft? I’ve stewed it for such a long time.
# 這個鴨子的皮太厚啦
This duck is far too thick-skinned,
# 比我的臉皮還厚
even when compared with me.
# 好啦 今天的視頻到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 我要吃飯啦
It’s my lunch time now.